USIA Artistic Ambassador Program Musical Commissions
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
USIA Artistic Ambassador Program Musical Commissions 1973-1988 (bulk 1983-1987)
ML31.U72
United States Information Agency. Artistic Ambassador Program
circa 50 items 4 containers 2.60 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
This collection consists of works commissioned by the United States Information Agency and other materials related to the organization’s Artistic Ambassador Program. It includes holograph music manuscripts, sketches, performance reviews, biographical materials, and administrative documents.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bacon, Ernst, 1898-1990.; Dello Joio, Norman, 1913-2008.; Finney, Ross Lee, 1906-1997.; Foss, Lukas, 1922-2009.; Gould, Morton, 1913-1996.; Hoiby, Lee.; Lees, Benjamin, 1924-2010.; Mayer, William, 1925-; Muczynski, Robert, 1929-; Perle, George, 1915-2009.; Robilette, John.; Rochberg, George.; Siegmeister, Elie, 1909-1991.; Smit, Leo, 1921-1999.
Organizations
United States Information Agency. Artistic Ambassador Program.; United States Information Agency. Artistic Ambassador Program.
Subjects
Music--Commissioning.; Music--Manuscripts.
Titles
United States Information Agency Artistic Ambassador Program musical commissions, 1973-1988
Form/Genre
Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Press releases.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Manuscripts commissioned for the USIA Artistic Ambassador Program and related materials were placed on deposit at or donated to the Library of Congress by the contributing composers and John Robilette between 1984 and 1988.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Two sound recordings were transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division.
Access and Restrictions
The USIA Artistic Ambassador Program Musical Commissions are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Organizational History
The United States Information Agency was established by President Dwight D. Eisenhower in August 1953 and was active until October 1, 1999. Its basic mandates were the Smith-Mundt Act of 1948 and the Fulbright-Hays Act of 1961. The Agency's stated mission was "to understand, inform, and influence foreign publics in promotion of the U.S. national interest, and to broaden the dialogue between Americans and U.S. institutions, and their counterparts abroad."
One aspect of this strategy involved the identification, promotion, and financial support of young, virtuoso American performers as "ambassadors" of international understanding and goodwill. Those who had yet to establish themselves as "big-time" artists were of primary interest. Following the success of a 1982 pilot program that sent pianist Robert Noland to tour France and Germany, USIA director Charles Z. Wick formally launched the Artistic Ambassador Program in April 1983 under the leadership of John Robilette and named pianist Arthur Greene the second Artistic Ambassador.
In 1984, four additional pianists were recruited to represent USIA: Michael Caldwell, Dean Kramer, Steve Warzycki, and Nancy Weems. The program continued to expand rapidly, and by the following year, eleven pianists had traveled to 38 countries, including the Soviet Union and China. By 1986 and 1987 respectively, the performance programs had also incorporated violin-piano duos and violoncello-piano duos. Touring efforts continued until the termination of the Program in 1989.
In addition to its support of performers, the Program sought commissioned works from eminent American composers, including Norman Dello Joio, Morton Gould, George Rochberg, and others. This marked one of the first dedicated efforts by the federal government to commission musical works for the purpose of promoting American culture abroad. Between 1983 and 1987, a total of 13 works were commissioned by the Program.
Scope and Content Note
The musical works commissioned for the USIA Artistic Ambassador Program date from 1982-1988. The "Music Manuscripts" series contains holograph manuscripts and/or sketches for all thirteen commissioned pieces, with Bacon's "Gunnison River" being the only exception. Two additional works commissioned by the USIA prior to 1982, but not for the Artistic Ambassador Program, are also included. Lukas Foss’ Fanfare was commissioned to commemorate the 50th anniversary of the Turkish Republic and was performed by the Presidential Symphony of Ankara in Istanbul with Foss conducting on June 28, 1973. Leo Smit’s Symphony of dances and songs was commissioned to commemorate the 100th anniversary of the establishment of U.S./Serbian diplomatic relations and was performed by the Belgrade Philharmonic with Smit conducting on November 6, 1981.
The "Research Materials" series contains memoranda, booklets, reviews, competition brochures, press releases, news clippings, and feature stories about the program’s inception, purpose, and active years. Biographical materials and images of several of the artistic ambassadors are also included.
Arrangement of the USIA Artistic Ambassador Program Musical Commissions
The USIA Artistic Ambassador Program Musical Commissions are organized in 2 series:
Music Manuscripts, 1973-1987
Research Materials, 1982-1988
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010561024
Container List
- Music Manuscripts, 1973-1987 (Box 1-2, OV)
  - Bacon, Ernst (Box 1)
    - The Gunnison River, Photo-reproduction of manuscript (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Dello Joio, Norman (Box 1)
    - Introduction and fantasies on a chorale tune (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Finney, Ralph (Box 1)
    - Narrative in retrospect, 1983 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Foss, Lukas (Box 1)
    - Fanfare, 1973, Printed parts and staging instructions; Not commissioned for Artistic Ambassador Program (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Central Park reel, 1987, Program notes and revised musical material on p. 16a/b (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Gould, Morton (Box 1)
    - Patterns for piano, 1984 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Hoiby, Lee (Box 1)
    - Ballade, op. 41, 1983 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Lees, Benjamin (Box 2)
    - Tableau, 1986 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Mayer, William (Box 2)
    - Abandoned bells, n.d. (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Muczynski, Robert (Box 2)
    - Dream cycle: op. 44, 1983, Accompanying cassette tape sent to MBRS (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Perle, George (Box 2)
    - Six new etudes, 1985, Laid in: Letter to J. Robilette; [1] p. (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Rochberg, George (Box OV 1)
    - Short sonatas, 1984, Accompanying cassette tape sent to MBRS (Box-folder OV 1/1)
  - Siegmeister, Elie (Box 2)
    - From these shores, 1986, Laid in: Composer's note; [1] p. (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Smit, Leo (Box OV 1)
    - Symphony of dances and songs, 1981, Laid in: Program notes; [5] p.; Not commissioned for Artistic Ambassador Program (Box-folder OV 1/2)
    - Dance card, 1985, Laid in: 2 letters to J. Robilette; [1] p. ea. (Box-folder 2/6)
- Research Materials, 1982-1988 (Box 3)
  - USIA file, 1983-1984, Includes biographies and images of Michael Caldwell, Dean Kramer, Steve Warzycki, and Nancy Weems. In addition, contains clippings, information on the Artistic Ambassador Program and its associated contacts, a list of performers/locations for commissioned works, reviews, press releases, and telegrams regarding Foss’ Fanfare. (Box-folder 3/1)
  - USIA file, 1982-1988, Includes memoranda, booklets, evaluations, reviews, audition brochures, press releases, and feature articles. (Box-folder 3/2)